Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is Chaf
Daled כ"ד. Chaf Daled. We are continuing the discussion about various things
you get lashes for and right now we're dealing with the interesting
things that have to do with the body, and so we dealt
with making a bald spot on the head for a dead person,
an incision in the flesh,
and actually no we've primarily been focused on the bald spot on
the head. The Mishna משנה Mishna also mentioned the cutting of the
sideburns, the cutting of the beard, and the incision in the flesh,
so that's what we're going to look at now. Okay, so hamakif
at rosho המקיף את ראשו, Hamakif at rosho, somebody who is makif
מקיף, makif, or again by the beard it uses the word mashchit
משחית, mashchit, which we'll see is a critical word which sort of
says that like use of scissors is okay, electric shavers we'll discuss,
but by the sideburns it says makif מקיף, makif, which is
echoing the word in the Torah תורה, Torah, but the question is
what different act does it describe? The reason people don't use a
shaver on the peot פאות peot is because it doesn't use the
word mashchit משחית, mashchit, so it could be that even any type
of cutting is a problem. Of course as we mentioned the other
day, according to a number of Rishonim ראשונים, Rishonim, Rashi רש"י Rashi
in particular and the Rivan ריב"ן Rivan whatever which is the commentary
we're dealing with now, it's only a problem when somebody completely cuts
them off, the complete like you know, and that's what the word
makif מקיף makif means, like to make a straight line cutting off
this whole section. Anyway, so the Gemara גמרא Gemara interestingly does not
discuss the details of that at all, so let's take a look
at the Gemara גמרא. Gemara. Tanu Rabbanan תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: at
rosho sof rosho את ראשו סוף ראשו, at rosho sof rosho, the
end of the head. Ve'eizehu sof rosho ואיזהו סוף ראשו? Ve'eizehu sof
rosho? Ze hamoshve tzadaiv leachorei ozno זה המשוה צדעיו לאחורי אזנו. Ze
hamoshve tzadaiv leachorei ozno. Now that really sounds like Rashi רש"י. Rashi.
Yes, sounds a lot like Rashi רש"י. Rashi. This is the one
that sort of makes
equal the side, tzadaiv צדעיו tzadaiv I think is the what do
you call it? Temples. How does he translate the word tzadaiv צדעיו?
tzadaiv? I believe that if we had what? Extremity. Extremity? I think
that when Rashi רש"י Rashi before said let me just look at
Rashi רש"י, Rashi, temples, yes. Okay, the temples to the back of
the ear, so if you start at the temple and you go
straight to the back of the ear you're sort of cutting this
whole section off, so it really sounds like that's the only thing,
which is interesting you know about how careful the practice is about
the sideburns. Can we argue otherwise? What? I don't know, I mean
Rambam רמב"ם Rambam some say forty hairs, any forty hairs within this,
like maybe that's conceptually the issue but maybe you're over even when
you do a portion of that or something, but it is interesting
the way that we have much more strict readings of that.
Where were we?
Okay. Ulepadachto leachorei ozno ולפדחתו ולאחורי אזנו Ulepadachto leachorei ozno and to
his and to his forehead. So basically the forehead and the back
of the ear and you sort of just make a straight line,
seems pretty clear. Okay so alright, Tani tana kamei deRav Chisda תני
תנא קמיה דרב חסדא, Tani tana kamei deRav Chisda, so a Tana
תנא Tana taught in front of Rav Chisda רב חסדא: Rav Chisda:
echad hamakif ve'echad hanikaf loke אחד המקיף ואחד הניקף לוקה. echad hamakif
ve'echad hanikaf loke. Whether you are the guy giving the haircut or
the guy getting the haircut you get lashes. Now that's an important
question right, because there's lo takifu לא תקיפו, lo takifu, so if
it refers to the act of cutting off it doesn't mean the
person who's letting somebody do it, so it's only the person who
is actually doing it, right? I mean a lot of things we
have like you know similar questions come up, I get a lot
of questions about like a whole questions of
sirus סירוס, sirus, of like of different forms for men or for
women about surgery that you know will basically make them you know
no longer able to have children, so the Torah תורה Torah says
right that you're not allowed to, bevasarkhem lo ta'asu בבשרכם לא תעשו,
bevasarkhem lo ta'asu, but the question is that you know the issur
איסור issur is primarily said about the one who's doing the surgery
not the one to whom the surgery is being done, right? But
nevertheless like you're making the decision, you're participating in it and so
on. Anyway so it's very interesting where we tend to focus on
the one to whom it's being done but the actual prohibition is
said on the one who's doing the act. Okay, so he says
even the one who's getting the haircut gets lashes, echad hamakif ve'echad
hanikaf loke אחד המקיף ואחד הניקף לוקה. echad hamakif ve'echad hanikaf loke.
Amar lei man de'achil tamrei be'arvilei loki אמר ליה מאן דאכיל תמרי
בארבילא לקי? Amar lei man de'achil tamrei be'arvilei loki? What? Somebody now
who's going to eat dates in a like like in a colander
are you going to give lashes to? Meaning it's like what? Somebody
who twiddles his thumbs you're going to give lashes to? I mean
it's an idiom but it basically means like you know he's doing
nothing. The guy now it's pretty funny it's not like he's doing
nothing, I mean he's the one who's initiating the whole process but
the still the point maybe so the question is is it a
problem of lashes? Is it a problem because it's a lav she'ein
bo ma'aseh לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she'ein bo ma'aseh and you're
being passive? When you say a guy who's eating dates are you
going to give lashes to, it sounds more than just that he's
being passive, it sounds like he's not doing any prohibition at all,
it sounds like he's saying the prohibition is only on the one
who's doing it. So are we asking that you shouldn't get lashes
because you're passive or are we asking that you shouldn't transgress because
the entire transgression is said in reference to the one who's doing
the act not in the one who's receiving to whom the act
is being done? Alright but so that's not exactly clear let's see
what the answer is. ואם תאמר לך מאני, V'im tomar lach mani,
if somebody says to you who said this crazy idea, excuse me,
not crazy, but who is, who said this person, who said this
idea that you get lashes even if it's being done to you?
You should respond back רבי יהודה היא דאמר לאו שאין בו מעשה
לוקין עליו. Rabbi Yehuda hi d'amar lav she'ein bo ma'aseh lokin alav.
So now it does seem like the problem issue wasn't whether you
were transgressing. He was willing to concede you were transgressing. What was
bothering him was that you were being passive. So he says this
doesn't make any sense, you're being passive. If this is going like
anybody, it's going like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says you get
lashes even for a passive transgression. But somehow we do learn out
from לא תקיפו Lo sakifu that according to this that the transgression,
it seems like nobody's debating that you transgress, the transgression is whether
you are being active or whether you are being passive, there's a
question of whether you get lashes. So the ריב"ן Rivan here asks,
ריב"ן Rivan right is the one who's looking like רש"י Rashi these
days, anyway asks like okay where do you learn out that even
the one to whom it's being done and he suggests maybe it's
the plural language that לא תקיפו, Lo sakifu, you know the fact
that it's in plural means that it refers both to the one
doing the act and to whom it's being done. Okay so the
one who we're still saying that he's being passive though? He's being
passive, you are transgressing. You can't think that way you know. Right
I understand, but if you weren't for this line you might have
said he's not transgressing any. No, you could have said like it's
a different kind of case in the משנה. Mishna. Yeah the case
in the משנה Mishna is the guy who's doing it. No, you
could say it's even both, like you know, but potentially depending on
how you... all right we're going to get... well we'll get to
that answer, I understand we'll get to that answer, okay but but
anyway there's two... but the first חידוש chidush is let's not ignore
the first חידוש, chidush, the first חידוש chidush is is that the
one to whom it's being done transgresses. Then there's a second level
of a question of does he get lashes. Okay but the first
thing that's not explicit in the משנה Mishna or in the פסוק
posuk is that he transgresses.
All right, so רבא אמר במקיף לעצמו ודברי הכל. Rava amar b'makkif
l'atzmo v'divrei hakol. You don't have to limit it to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, you can have it that the guy who actually is
giving himself a haircut. So now okay you give yourself a haircut
you only get one, you get lashes from מקיף. makkif. But he
says no you also are getting lashes for ניקף. nikaf. Nobody is
disagreeing with the חידוש chidush that the one to whom it's being
done also transgresses. Seems like for some reason that's just taken for
granted. Question is how is he doing an action? So one answer
is he's not doing an action and he gets lashes anyway. The
other answer is he's doing an action, he's actively getting it done
to himself because he's giving it to himself. So he is both
the מקיף makkif and he's the active ניקף. nikaf. Okay so he's
the one to whom it's getting done and him getting it done
to himself is in an active way. So he would get two
sets of lashes. רב אשי אמר במסייע ודברי הכל, Rav Ashi amar
b'mesayei'a v'divrei hakol, which is what, which is what Michael said, that
you actually are participating in the act, okay, so like you know
when the barber says tip your head this way, hold it this
way, so if you like are helping out that's an enough of
an action to say you've actively transgressed. Now by the way this
leads to an interesting discussion in the פוסקים poskim whether when by
a normal עבירה aveira would we say there's an idea of מסייע
mesayei'a or is it only here where we start with the knowledge
that you are transgressing. Somehow we take it for granted for whatever
reason, everybody here's assuming that the ניקף nikaf is included in the
prohibition. Everybody agrees that just by having it done you're transgressing and
the only issue we have to do is to say that you
get lashes. So there מסייע mesayei'a is enough to say you get
lashes. But let's take something that it was never said for the
person to whom it's being done. For example there's a whole question,
interesting question that we were just doing in the ישיבה yeshiva with
the guys about you know a woman who goes to the מקוה
mikvah on Friday night and the practice was that women would totally
cut their nails down to the quick, actually it's a very interesting
area of הלכה Halacha because it really technically shouldn't have been required
because it's only question of dirt under the nail so if you
clean it well enough but the practice developed to completely cut the
nails and there's actually some communities in which the women rebelled and
they refused to go to the מקוה mikvah if the rabbis were
going to insist that they cut their nails. So anyway, so yeah,
so anyway but and you know nowadays I think in modern Orthodox
communities like you know they do not ask the women to cut
their nails they just make sure that they're clean or whatever, okay
but anyway in a community in which it was completely sort of
assumed that a woman had to totally cut her nail down to
like the quick, she comes to the מקוה mikvah Friday night she
forgot to cut her nails. So some פוסקים poskim would say okay
look it's only a חומרא chumra basically just clean the nail go
to the מקוה mikvah anyway and others say nope she absolutely has
to cut her nails. So what should she do? She should get
a non-Jew to help her cut the nails on שבת, Shabbos, like
to talk about like a חומרא chumra that leads to a קולא
kula right? So אמירה לנכרי amira l'nochri is it two דרבנן d'rabanans
is it one דרבנן, d'rabanan, so anyway within that discussion came the
issue about wait but she's מסייעת mesaya'at because you know when you
have to hold your hand in a certain way. So that gets
to an interesting question of is this idea of מסייע mesayei'a now
clear? Clearly the one who's doing the מלאכה, mela'cha, I mean she's
not commanded or whatever, is the non-Jew who's doing the cutting, right?
You're not doing the מלאכה, mela'cha, but how much is your מסייע
mesayei'a make you a somehow also a
transgressor? Okay so anyway then they bring in this discussion here by
the haircut etc. So it's inter- and you know the distinction is
that here it's clear that you start by being a transgressor, we
take it for granted the prohibition applies to the ניקף, nikaf, the
issue of מסייע mesayeia is only to get the person to be
liable in lashes, to get them active and liable in lashes. It'd
be different if the person was not transgressing, right, personally transgressing, how
much would the מסייע mesayeia make them a transgressor? Are you understand
the difference? Here you're a transgressor, the מסייע mesayeia makes you an
active transgressor to get lashes. It's different in a case where you're
not a transgressor and how much does מסייע mesayeia make you a
transgressor? All right, anyway, so that's the issue about the פאות, peyot,
no real discussion on the part that I think most would interest
us, which is what type of cutting, what section of the head
is and so on. ומשחית פאת זקנו, v'hamaschit pat zekano, somebody who
destroys the corners of the beard, which as we said yesterday, the
פאה peia of the ראש rosh is from here, the way the
ריב"ן Rivan explains it, from you know the bone here by the
ear to the temple, so that's the issue of הקפה, hakafah, and
the פאת הזקן peiat hazakan from the same point but going down
to here, presumably to here and one here, so it would be
like this whole area. Presumably it's like you make a path going
down here, okay and it's that whole area. But here the, so
not including the beard, the mustache which we mentioned, seems like you
could actually use a straight razor to cut your mustache. I don't
know anybody who does that and I haven't looked into it, but
tentatively it certainly seems that that, you know, that that's not included
in the זקן, zakan, in the beard. As Charlie pointed out the
other day, in the Amish basically don't cut their beard at all,
but they cut their mustache. That's presumably based on that. Anyway, but
here we're going to talk about this. This is an issue of
משחית, maschit, okay? And here so let's take a look what this
is. And on the one hand it would seem to apply to
like any amount of hair, but only an act that is considered
to be השחתה. hashchata. So that's particularly what we're going to work
to describe. Actually you just do it the other way around, can't
you? That it's not השחתה hashchata since you... you could. All right,
well we'll see ישחית, yishchat, fine, you could. Okay, let's see, anyway
we're going to get back to that in a minute because we're
going to... because the משנה mishna moves back and forth in the
discussion about the beard. Okay, so first, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, פאת
זקנו, pat zekano, סוף זקנו, sof zekano, the edge of the beard,
ואיזו סוף זקנו, v'eizu sof zekano, שיבולת זקנו. shibolet zekano. So the
שיבולת shibolet is like a, is what? שיבולת? shibolet? Yeah, well it's
a bundle, it's also isn't a... yeah like a stalk or something.
So presumably it means the way I understand the ריב"ן Rivan meaning,
it means like the path that goes when you're moving from this
point to this point, it's sort of like you know, so it's
like a, it's like a sheath, like a path or so. Okay,
what are those called? People have that, like chops or something, you
know they just... what? Mutton chops or something. Anyway. All right.
Okay, so we'll get back to the beard in a minute. Okay,
והמשרט שריטה אחת. v'hamasaret srita achat. Now the idea of one incision
in the flesh for a dead person, so even if it's five
incisions for the separate person, you get five lashes, presumably separate התראה,
hatara, which I don't understand why that's such a חידוש chiddush or
one incision for five dead people you get five lashes. That's a
big חידוש, chiddush, but I don't understand how you define that it
was for five over five dead people unless maybe the התראה hatara
explicitly identified that. So let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, ושרט לנפש, v'saret l'nefesh, an incision in the
flesh. יכול אפילו שרט על ביתו שנפל ועל ספינתו שטבעה בים, yachol
afilu sarat al beito shenafal v'al sefino shetavah bayam, maybe an incision
even on something else you're angst about and it's not over a
grief of a mourning. תלמוד לומר לנפש, talmud lomar l'nefesh, for the...
for a soul. So it's a mourning ritual. אינו חייב אלא על
המת בלבד, eino chayav ela al hameit bilvad, only if it's for
somebody who died. מניין למשרט חמש שריטות על מת אחד שהוא חייב
על כל אחת ואחת, minayin l'masarei chamesh sritot al meit echad shehu
chayav al kol achat v'achat, how do you know if you do
five separate incisions for one person who died you get five sets
of lashes? תלמוד לומר ושרט, talmud lomar v'saret, okay, the use of
the noun means for each individual incision. Again, since you would, presumably
you'd have to get a separate warning for each one and then
I'm not exactly sure of the חידוש. chiddush. לחייב על כל שריטה
ושריטה. l'chayev al kol srita v'srita. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer,
maybe if it's like the גמרא gemara before that spoke about your
five fingers on five separate bald spots. Maybe here you manage to
do, that'd be cool, like you could actually have like a fork,
you know, and you stick it and you do... right? And you
do... course! So you do all at the same time. So that
would be, that would be an example where it would be one
התראה, hatara, four multiple, four parallel acts, okay,
and therefore you'd get five sets of lashes. So that would actually
be the חידוש chiddush similar to the issue of the bald spots,
if they're all done in parallel. לחייב על כל שריטה ושריטה. l'chayev
al kol srita v'srita. רבי יוסי אומר מניין למשרט שריטה אחת על
חמישה מתים שהוא חייב על כל אחת ואחת, Rabbi Yose omer minayin
l'masarei srita achat al chamisha meitim shehu chayav al kol achat v'achat,
how do you even know one incision for five, in our משנה
mishna it was סתם, stam, here we see it's the position of
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, that you get five sets of lashes again,
somehow it's made explicit that it's done for five people who died.
תלמוד לומר לנפש, talmud lomar l'nefesh, לחייב
על כל נפש ונפש, l'chayev al kol nefesh v'nefesh, for every person
is a separate prohibition, so one act over five is seen as
if you piled up five separate acts for five separate in one
cutting. Which, what... what the Rosh says? I don't know. I don't
know, I don't know how he's מדייק *m'dayek* it from the פסוק
*pasuk*. Where is לנפש *Laneffesh*? ושרט לנפש לא תתנו בבשרכם *Vsaret Laneffesh
lo sitnu bivsarchem*. Okay, it's there's two פסוקים pesukim, *psukim*. ושרט לנפש
*Vsaret Laneffesh*. Okay, there's two פסוקים psukim *psukim*. לחייב על כל נפש
ונפש *L'chayev al kol nefesh venefesh*. And he asks Michael's question. והספידה
לביתו *V'haspido l'beiso* שנפלה ספינתו שטבעה בים *shenafela sfinaso shetava bayam*? לנפש
*Laneffesh* comes to say that it's only in the context of a
dead. How do you learn that it means for every dead person
it's considered even one incision for multiple dead persons it's considered multiple
transgressions? Where do you learn that from? סבר רבי יוסי *Savar Rabbi
Yosei* שריטה seritah, וגדידה אחת היא *srita ugedida achas hi*. No, because
there's another פסוק *pasuk* that says לא תתגודדו *lo sisgodedu*. Okay, and
everybody agrees that the word לא תתגודדו *lo sisgodedu* also refers to
the making of incisions in the flesh. Okay. Now, the general assumption
is that לנפש *laneffesh*, שרט *saret* means an incision by your
like you know using your body like with your fingernails and גדידה
gedidah *gedida* means like using something like a knife or something. Okay.
And that's normally explained why you need two פסוקים *psukim*. But he
says both the word שרט *saret* or you know לא תתגודדו *lo
sisgodedu* and the word גדידה *gedida* both refer to whether the incision
is by hand or by knife. So since that's true it's actually
redundant, right? Because it only had to say one since they're both
describing the exact same case. And they both say לנפש *laneffesh* because
it says לא תתגודדו ולא תשימו קרחה בין עיניכם למת *lo sisgodedu
vlo sasimu korcha bein eineichem lamet*. So the word למת *lamet* applies
by גדידה *gedida* as well. So he basically says you have לא
תתגודדו למת *lo sisgodedu lamet* and ושרט לנפש *vsaret laneffesh*.
What's the פסוק *pasuk* Michael? לא ישרטו שרטה בראשם ופאת זקנם לא
יגלחו ufe'at zekanam lo yegaleichu *lo yisretu sarta berosham ufas zkanam lo
yegalechu*. No, that's by the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*. ושרט לנפש *Vsaret laneffesh*.
Okay, so it's ושרט לנפש *vsaret laneffesh* and לא תתגודדו ולא תשימו
קרחה בין עיניכם על מת meit. *lo sisgodedu vlo sasimu korcha bein
eineichem al mes*. So therefore you have לא תתגודדו על מת *lo
sisgodedu al mes* and ושרט לנפש *vsaret laneffesh* and for him they're
describing the exact same act. So one of those is extra. So
the extra word
is coming to teach you even if it's for multiple dead persons
it was multiple transgressions. סבר רבי יוסי *Savar Rabbi Yosei* שריטה וגדידה
אחת היא *srita ugedida achas hi* וכתיב התם למת *uchsiv hasam lamet*.
So therefore since there says למת *lamet* and here says לנפש *laneffesh*,
one of them is to tell you that it's multiple transgressions even
if it's only one act. All right. אמר amar שמואל *Amar Shmuel*
המשרט בכלי חייב chayav. *hamsaret bichli chayav*. If somebody does שריטה *srita*
with a vessel, a utensil, a tool like a knife, then you
transgress. Now, as we've already said implicitly, yes you transgress but normally
we would have put it in the category of גדידה *gedida*. He's
calling it המשרט *hamsaret*. So it sounds like he's holding like רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yosei* that the word משרט *mseret* includes both the idea
of hand and the idea of using some type of a tool.
Okay. מיתיבי *Meisivei* שריטה וגדידה אחת היא *srita ugedida achas hi*. We
have a ברייתא *braisa* that says yes they're basically the same prohibition
an incision in the flesh for a dead body. אלא ששריטה ביד
וגדידה בכלי *ela she'srita beyad ugedida bichli* that one is by hand
and one is with some type of a tool. So why is
שמואל *Shmuel* by שמואל *Shmuel* calling it שריטה בכלי *srita bichli*? It
sounds like he's describing that it's... well it's really not a question,
everybody agrees it's prohibited and you get lashes but it seems like
he's putting it in the שריטה *srita* category. But our ברייתא *braisa*
puts it in the גדידה *gedida* category. הוא דאמר כרבי יוסי *Hu
de'amar k'Rabbi Yosei*, he says like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosei* because we
just said a minute ago that to explain why רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yosei* the word למת *lamet* is extra is because he doesn't make
a distinction between the word שריטה *srita* and גדידה *gedida*. Fine. Okay.
But anyway one of the things we also learned from here is
A, it doesn't matter whether it's your hand or with a tool,
and also that the משנה Mishna *mishna* that says you get multiple
lashes if it's for one incision for multiple people is only a
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosei* position. Okay. See and are we still saying
I know I asked this already but look at this. Do you
gotta draw blood? What if it's just like this? Oh I see
your point. Yeah, I mean, you're right. I assume it's with drawing
blood, it's not like a scratch like the word שריטה *srita* but
I didn't have a chance to look at it. I could quickly
check what רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* says.
Let me check רמב"ם Rambam
*Rambam*. I'll check רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* for you. ושרט לנפש *Vsaret laneffesh*.
אחד כהן Kohen ששרט חמש והוא שישרוט בבשרו כחייב על כל נפש
ונפש *Echad kohen she'saret chamesh v'hu sheyisros bivsaro k'chayav al kol nefesh
venefesh*. גדידה ושריטה אחת היא *Gedida usrita achas hi*. שרטו בבשרם
*Sartu bivsaram*... No,
רמב"ם Rambam
*Rambam* does not describe what defines שריטה *srita*. It's a very good
question. You're right. I mean, the basic question Michael's asking is a
very good question. Like how much of an incision is an incision?
Does it have to draw blood? Does it have to be thick?
Does it have to whatever? It's a very good question.
Is
that
some of the thing you see now for flagellation that some Jews
do in religious? Yeah, that would not be... that's the point that
it's only... Now we're going to get to another way in which
it was done in a second. So let me just get to
that. Hold on, let me just read that. Someone can do it
even for yourself, right? Yeah, that is correct. You're still an איסור
to be חובל בעצמו, chovel b'atzmo, but it's not something that generally
speaking you'd get lashes for. Okay, but yes, that's a good point
too, you know. To just wound yourself, you're not able—like there is
a prohibition that wounding other people, wounding yourself. So that's a good
point too. Okay, let's take a look at—but no, the question about
whether you have to draw blood is a very good one. Let's
just get to the two dots and then I'll take the other
question. תני תנא קמי דרבי יוחנן: Tani tana kaman d'Rabbi Yochanan: על
מת בין ביד בין בכלי חייב. Al meit bein beyad bein bichli
chayav.
So for a dead person, whether you use your hand or whether
you use a utensil, a tool, you're חייב. chayav As we said,
whether you want to call it גדידה or whether you want to
call it שריטה, everybody agrees it's prohibited. ועל עבודת כוכבים ביד חייב
בכלי פטור. V'al avodat kochavim beyad chayav bichli patur.
By עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, you're only חייב chayav. if you do
it by hand, not if you do it with a utensil. Now
what by עבודה זרה? Avoda Zara? So we're going to see that
this was—making incisions in the flesh was a classic type of a
pagan
ritual. Okay, now,
so interestingly, רמב"ם understands that most of the things that we're discussing
in our משנה Mishna about the bald spots and the incisions and
the cutting of the hair—and we're going to get to the tattooing—that
all of those, the רמב"ם in מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevukhim basically says
that the reasons they're prohibited, most of those, was because they were
associated with pagan rituals. Okay, so I mean certainly if you think
about now... I mean the idea about the ritual about over-mourning, right?
Now you could have said the Torah maybe just wants to forbid
excessive, you know, acts of mourning. Right? It's not particularly because it's
pagan. But still, you know, the fact that you're—it is, you know—but
the רמב"ם understands that these things are forms of pagan ritual. So
there could be a ritual that's a mourning ritual that's not specifically
an act of worship. It's just a ritual done by pagans when
they mourn, is that they make incisions. You understand the difference between
a ritual and an act of worship? But here it's saying that
they could actually do incisions in the flesh as a type of
worship. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says: But that would only
be when they would do it by hand. So the גמרא Gemara
says: ואיפכא כתיב? Ve'ipcha ketiv? But what do you mean, the verse
says the opposite? That the ritual is done for—the worship ritual is
done with a utensil, with like a tool. ויתגדדו כמשפטם, Vayisgodedu kemishpatam,
they made incisions as was their practice, בחרבות וברמחים, becharvot uveramachim,
with swords and with spears.
That's the case of הר כרמל Har Carmel as you said. אלא
אימא: Ela eima: ביד פטור בכלי חייב. Beyad patur bichli chayav. Fine,
reverse it. With the hands you're פטור, patur, with a utensil or
whatever you're חייב. chayav Now, the question is: חייב chayav what? If
it's a normal עבודה זרה Avoda Zara that's normally worshipped this way,
then you don't have to identify it for me. There's a generic
principle. There's a principle that, you know, any particular עבודה avodah that
is distinctive for that עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, you're חייב מיתה chayav
mita if you worship it that way, right? So what's the point
of saying this? And maybe if there happens to be some עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara out there that the way to do it is
with a hand and not with a כלי, kli, you'd be חייב
chayiv. for the hand and not with a כלי. kli. Like, what
is the point of trying to describe this as a unique—as a
practice? Since the general rule is, either you have the four standard
practices—bowing down, right, offering sacrifices, etc.—or you have what happens to be
distinctive to that עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. What's the point of mentioning
this? So the way תוספות Tosafot explains it is if you might
remember, there's forms of adulation and worship, etc., that is שלא כדרכו,
shelo kedarko, that you're not—you don't get the death penalty, but you
still get lashes. The משנה mishna mentioned hugging, kissing, other types of
forms of adulation. So what we never really I think fully explored,
because a lot we explore like when do you get מיתה, mita,
when are you deserving of the death penalty, is what describes an
act of adulation or worship that's שלא כדרכו shelo kedarko that you
would get lashes for, right? Like, you know, let's say somebody was
פוער עצמו, po'er atzmo, you know, to a Zeus. You wouldn't say,
oh, that's an act of כבוד kavod and you get lashes for
עבודה שלא כדרכו, avodah shelo kedarko, right? But kissing it would be.
Well, does it have—you know, what defines what are those acts? So
that's what the תוספות Tosafot sort of says here is going on.
That we are saying since it was so standard type of a
pagan practice
to, you know, to do this type of incisions in the flesh,
so that would always be—considered to be like a type—whatever god the
person was worshipping, even if it was not a normal type of
an act done to that god in particular, since it was a
generic type of an act of worship, you know, that would still
be an
עבודה שלא כדרכו avodah shelo kedarko and you would get lashes. And
if they kissed it's similar to
kissing. And if you did something that in your mind was an
act of כבוד, kavod, but nobody thought it was, like you were
פוער עצמו poer atzmo to it, because you were a פעור Peor
worshiper, you'd get off scot-free. Okay? So anyway, the point here is
that this become is seen as a type of an act of
respect or a standard type of worship that even if it's not
the normal for that god, and therefore it's not חייב מיתה, chayiv
mitah, it's still an עבודה שלא כדרכה avodah shelo kedarkah and you
get lashes. Yes? Yes, Charlie, you had a question? You're alright. So
more lenient for the עבודה זרה avodah zarah than for the מת.
Yeah. Which is not -- well, it's not lenient. Right. But I
mean, that's -- I understand, but that is the scope of what
is considered the normal thing in that case. Okay. Why were you
so strict by עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? What can I tell you?
It has to fall in the right parameters. וחייב על הראש. Vechayiv
al harosh. Okay, now. וחייב chayiv on the head. So it basically
is the משנה mishna? says, what's the משנה? mishna Now we're getting
back to the hair cutting. So the משנה mishna? says...
where were we?
...I don't know where it says וחייב על הראש. vechayiv al harosh.
Where is that phrase in the משנה? mishna It says על הראש
שתים אחת מכאן ואחת מכאן. al harosh shtayim achat mikan veachat mikan.
They must be sticking in the word וחייב. vechayiv. Anyway, so you
have the two sideburns on each side. Okay? So what are those
two sideburns? So מחוי ליה רב ששת בין פירקי רישא. Machvei lei
Rav Sheshet bein pirkei reisha. So רב
ששת Rav Sheshet showed and demonstrated it was between the joints of
the head, which is not very helpful for us. Like, show us
what he demonstrated. But again, the way the רשב"ם Rashbam or whatever
-- the יב"ן Yavan explains it. Are -- you have a picture
there? Sexton? Sexton says a picture. Oh, all right. It's between --
it's between the temple and the sideburns. Okay? At -- between the
temple and the
-- let's take a look. Let me -- want me to show
it on the -- yeah, parts of the head. Edges of the
beard. Yeah, okay. So, wait -- although... he only shows five things.
Yes, he does. I mean, he shows three and then he just
repeats it on the other side. Okay? Although, right. So here, it's
basically the same thing I was showing. Oops, no, I don't know
what I did. All right, anyway. So from the -- here it's
from the temple to the bone, and from here it's this bone
and then this part and then like this part of your jaw
and then this. But basically, this bone is the key. Okay? So
this bone in the middle of your ear. From this bone to
the temple is your sideburns and from this bone down all the
way to your chin is, you know, one side of your beard.
All right. Okay. ועל הזקן חמש שתים מכאן ושתים מכאן ואחת מלמטה.
Veal hazakan chamesh shtayim mikan ushtayim mikan veachat milmata. מחוי
ליה רב ששת בין פירקי דיקנא. Machvei lei Rav Sheshet bein pirkei
dikna. So רב ששת Rav Sheshet demonstrated between the joints of the
beard, which was again not helpful for us. I'm sure it was
very helpful for them. רבי אליעזר אומר אם נטלן כולם כאחת אינו
חייב אלא אחת. Rabbi Eliezer omer im netalan kulam keachat eino chayiv
ela achat. If you do them all at once, you only transgress
once. כסבר חד לאו הוא. Kasavar chad lav hu. It's one prohibition.
Okay? Now again, that's not -- so what does that mean though?
I mean, does that mean -- I mean, what the חכמים Chachamim
say, if you say don't do it, you're going to be cutting
the corners of your beard and the guy says "I don't care"
and he does this, he gets three sets of lashes? I mean,
whatever, you know, why is that different than the נזיר nazir that's
drinking the whole day? Like I don't really get what their debate
is, you know? If you get multiple warnings, then presumably רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer would agree that it's multiple lashes. If you only get
one warning, presumably the חכמים Chachamim would agree it's only one lash.
I don't exactly get what their debate is. Unless you're doing it
at like, simultaneously like the case before, maybe that's the debate. Anyway,
moving on. ואינו חייב עד שיטלנו בתער. Ve'eino chayiv ad sheyitlenu beta'ar.
Now we get to the important question about what type of --
of cutting of the beard is described as cutting. So the משנה
Mishnah. says only if you use a razor, not if you use
a scissors or a -- or a tweezers. Okay? But then you
have the position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says even if
you use a tweezers. תנו רבנן ופאת זקנם לא יגלחו. Tanu rabanan:
ufe'at zekanam lo yegaleichu. יכול אפילו גילחו במספרים יהיה חייב. Yachol afilu
gileicho bemisparayim yehei chayiv. Maybe even if he used scissors? תלמוד לומר
לא תשחית. Talmud lomar: lo tashchit. Do not destroy. Presumably scissors are
not described as destroying because they don't get right to the root.
Okay? I'll just use that as the explanation right now. That's what
the רשב"ם Rashbam says. אי לא תשחית יכול ילקטנו במלקט ורהיטני יהיה
חייב. Ee lo tashchit yachol yelaktenu bemalket verahitani yehei chayiv. Oh, so
if it's all about destroying and getting to the root, so if
you use tweezers, you would get to the root, so maybe you
would be חייב. chayav Okay? תלמוד לומר לא יגלחו. Talmud lomar: lo
yegaleichu. Right? So it's these two פסוקים, right? One by ופאת זקנם
לא יגלחו yegaleichu by the כהנים and ולא תשחית את פאת זקנך
velo tashchit et pe'at zekanecha by ישראל. Yisrael. And we read them
again not as different לאווין, lavin, but we read them together and
you need both aspects of it. You need both the יגלחו yegaleichu?
and the תשחית. tashchit. So the תשחית tashchit is it has to
get to the root. What's the יגלחו? yegaleichu? So in what way
is tweezers not יגלחו? yigalechu Right? The -- what this makes it
clear, this is very important in terms of the discussion of פאות.
peyot. It says דרך גילוח. derech giluch. That's what the ריב"ן Rivan
says. But I would have said -- I mean it says a
razor and scissors is גילוח. giluach. Okay? Let me just show you.
Okay?
So you've got like this. You've got scissors.
Razor and tweezers. Okay, what it's saying is that you need to
be
יגלחו yigalechu, and תשחית. tashchit. Okay, so it says a razor is
both, let me just get to a check, razor is תשחית tashchit
and יגלחו, yigalechu, a scissors is not תשחית tashchit and it is
יגלחו, yigalechu and a tweezers is not יגלחו yigalechu? and it is
תשחית. tashchit. So you're only חייב hayyav for a razor. Okay, so
we can understand that the scissors is not תשחית tashchit because it
doesn't get to the root. A tweezers gets to the root. In
what way is it not יגלחו? yigalechu. But scissors and razors are
יגלחו. yigalechu Okay, so Michael says, and this is what the ריבב״ן
Rivvan says, razor and scissors is normal and tweezers is not normal.
Okay, and now that gets into interesting questions, who defines norms and
so on. Okay, but that's what the ריבב״ן Rivvan says. Another very
reasonable thing to say is that razors and scissors use a blade
and do an act of cutting, whereas tweezers don't do an act
of cutting, and maybe יגלחו yigalechu, refers to an act of cutting.
Okay, so the thing that is prohibited is something that gets to
the root and is גילוח, giluach, which maybe means cutting, which maybe
means normal, etc. Okay, who knows exactly what גילוח giluach means? So
now the question is, what is the story with electric razors and
can you use electric razors? Okay, so some want to say that
what really, that electric razors are basically, well, they're an act of
cutting, it's normal, etc., and the whole thing they focus on is
is it תשחית? tashchit? Does it get right to the root? Okay,
because if it gets super, you know, because since it's not cutting
against the skin and it's more, it's got the, a normal way
a razor works is it's got an electric razor is it's got
a foil, and the hair goes into the foil and then the
blades cut it. So since the foil stands between the skin and
the blades, it never gets fully against the skin as much
as a razor does. So some want to say that that's the
reason that an electric shaver's not a problem, because it doesn't get
to the root. And that's why people will discuss, oh, but this
electric razor is a problem, because what they're saying is this one
gets such a close shave that it is getting to the root
and it is a problem. Doesn't Norelco advertise shaves as close as
a blade? I understand, that's exactly, so then some people say, hey,
you can't trust the advertising, it's not true. I actually found a
whole scientific study about exactly how close it gets and whatever. Okay,
it doesn't get as close. Okay, anyway, so wait, wait, wait, one
explanation is that electric shavers are not תשחית tashchit because they don't
get to the bottom. The other, right, these, well, right, the other
way to argue that they're okay is in this category, it's not
normal or it's not cutting. So let's start with the normal. So
the question is how do you define normal? So normal nowadays, normal
in the time when the פסוקים were being given, in the time
of חז״ל? Chazal? So that might depend. If you say normal in
the time of חז״ל Chazal or the Torah, okay, electric shavers weren't
invented yet or weren't normal. The original patent for the first electric
shaver was in April 1928. Fine. You can, so if you'll say
normal nowadays, you could debate, meaning it is normal, it is widespread,
but it's not like normal for people who want to get the
closest shave, right, like if you want to get a certain type
of a shave, go to the barber, you're going to use a
blade, not. Right, so the normal is debatable, how you define normal.
Okay, how about the issue of cutting? Well, a shaver definitely cuts.
Okay, I mean, you know, but here's the
issue. Some want to say that the difference between the razors and
the scissors, and I guess it's a form of לא תשחית lo
tashchit but this really then gets to יגלחו, that the reason scissors
are different than a razor is not the issue of whether it
gets to the root or not, but it's that a scissors is
a cutting action and a razor is a, like, you know, what,
how would you describe it different, is a slicing action, right, it's
a, a scissors is a two-blade cutting action and a razor is
a slicing action. And if that is the difference here, not the
question of does it get to the root or not, but the
difference of cutting versus slicing, so then there's a whole מחלוקת machlokes
by electric razors. On the one hand, it goes through the foil
and the foil holds it, which lets the blade cut it. Okay,
so that's like a scissors if you think about it. And but
others will say no, that's only in order to protect the skin,
the blade is really so sharp it can do it itself. Bottom
line is it's not true, the blade is not sharp enough, the
only you need friction, the reason a razor is able to cut
is because you either have to hold the hair tight or because
you're cutting against the skin. Okay, you, so you're, you know, so
the reason a shaver cuts is because the other foil is holding
it. So that's another way of explaining the difference here, right, and
to therefore say that it's okay. But weren't you also moving it
down, in which case then you're sliding and you're doing sort of
like a, couldn't you argue that? But you're moving it down, so
you're doing sort of a slight thing. Yeah, but it doesn't matter,
no, because inside the mechanism, what's happening is that it's being held
and scissors are cutting it. Okay, so that gets to all those
questions and which types of shavers you think may or may not
be a problem determines how you determine the difference between this. Now
the way we know, because why didn't we just start with an
assumption that oh my gosh, it's so close to the edge, it's
clearly more like a razor. So there's actually a debate, it's not
explicit in the גמרא, Gemara, but the תוספות Tosafot in a different
place develops the idea based on a discussion by a נזיר. Nazir.
It's not ironically, it's not explicit here that מספרים כעין
תער misparayim ke-ein ta'ar is okay. Okay, even if scissors, even if
they're functioning close to the idea of a razor, they're still okay
because they're scissors. So the question was, well what makes them okay?
I mean even if they're scissors right up against the skin, it's
okay. What makes that, what makes that different than a razor at
the end of the day, if it's so close? And that leads
to the following possibilities that it's different. Even though it's so close
it's not ממש, mamash, you know, at the root. Okay, or even
though it's so close, it's still cutting versus slicing. Or even though
it's so close, it's still not fully דרכו. darko. So there's like
three explanations why this is
okay. And then the idea is well now apply that to a
shaver, okay, and that's the question. Maybe a shaver is cutting at
the root. Okay, maybe a shaver is slicing, maybe it's not cutting.
Maybe a shaver is דרכו, darko, right? All those are the debates
around using a shaver. What did you say the reason is that
a shaver isn't...
that's why I was saying, but some people will still argue that.
Some people want to claim that a shaver is slicing and not
cutting. Okay, so that's based on how you understand what this is
and acknowledging that this is even okay, right? Scissors getting a close
cut like a razor. Now, by the פאת הראש, pe'at ha-rosh, מספרים
כעין תער misparayim ke-ein ta'ar are not okay. So that you know,
here, right? So getting close to the skin here even with the
scissors is not okay. Why? Because it doesn't use the word תשחית
tash-chit and so on. Okay, it doesn't use the same verbs. Okay,
but I mean again, תוספות Tosafot develops this idea and that's the
generally accepted הלכה. halakha. Getting around the... but so there are two
questions: How is he doing the act of cutting and how much
is prohibited? Okay, so on the one hand this allowance of מספרים
כעין תער misparayim ke-ein ta'ar does not apply to the sideburns. Okay,
and on the other hand though, sideburns might only be forbidden if
it's like ממש mamash cutting the whole thing off, at least in
the simple sense of the גמרא. Gemara. We tend to read it
more strictly. So where at the middle bump there is that... that
bump is the difference between the halakhic that governs the... it comes
down to the bump. Yeah, and then the question always is like,
it sounds like the height of the bump. You could go as
high, if you wanted to do the lower part of the bone,
you'd go all the way down here, but it sounds like it's
the height of the bump. Yeah, and also what about the trimmers?
That's also a scissors. Trimmers work the same way as the shaver,
yeah. Same razor foil. Right, but it works the same way. Actually
the trimmers are more obviously a scissors action. You know, you see
really the two blades sort of. Okay, so if anybody wants to
see, I got a תשובה teshuvah on this whole thing on the
Lindenbaum website with pictures, with pictures, yeah, I'll send that down. I'll
send out the link. Okay, so okay, where are we? יכול יחתם
לא שידי אילו לא שידי יכול אם ליקט במלקט וברהיטני יהיה חייב
תלמוד לומר לא יגילחו. yakhol ikhtam lo she-yaddi ilu lo she-yaddi yakhol
im liket bi-melaket u-ve-reitani ye-hayyev talmud lomar lo yigale'u. I don't know,
some type of tweezers. What do they say in English? Poly-s... I
don't know, tweezers are tweezers. Okay, anyway, הכיצד גילוח שיש בו השחתה?
haketzad gillu'ach she-yesh bo haskhatah? It has to be both a shaving,
which might mean like a blade action or normal type of a
thing, and it has to be destructive, which means like getting to
the root. הוי אומר זה תער. hevei omer zeh ta'ar. That is
a razor. But of course then the question is what exactly is
the line between razor and shaver? Why? What do they say between
two types of... azerah plane? I don't know what that means. There
you go, now you know. רבי אליעזר אומר אפילו ליקט במלקט וברהיטני
חייב. Rabbi Eliezer omer afillu liket bi-melaket u-ve-reitani hayyav. Fine, right. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says even if you use the tweezers you're חייב
because he focuses... it's similar to the previous רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says also, he doesn't want to distinguish between
the five corners, he says it's all one. Meaning, how is it
similar? One is lenient, one is strict. Because it seems like he's
focusing less on process and more on end result. If you focus
on process, you say only if you use certain types of implements,
but then maybe each corner is a separate prohibition. He says I
don't care if at the end of the day you're head... you
know, it's all about the creating the result. So even if you
use tweezers, but then it's not... it's one prohibition, it's not multiple
prohibitions, it's achieving the end result. So the גמרא Gemara says: מה
נפשך? ma nafshakh? Make up your mind. אי גמר גזירה שוה, i
gamar gezerah shavah, if he links the two requirements together, השחתה וגילוח.
haskhatah ve-gillu'ach. By בתער ta'ar he should have to require a razor.
If he doesn't apply גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah and if he doesn't,
מספריים נמי misparayim nami so then even a scissors would be a
problem, meaning he basically favors the word להשחית. le-hashchit. He focuses on
does it completely destroy? Does it get to the root? Okay, why
does he favor that word over the word גילוח? giluach? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says... so the גמרא's Gemara answer is לעולם גמר
גזירה שוה. le-olam gamar gezeirah shavah. Yes, he does apply both words.
So how does he achieve גילוח? giluach? וקסבר הא נמי גילוח עבדי,
ve-kasavar ha nami giluach avdi, you know what? Plucking the hairs is
also גילוח. giluach. Now, how is plucking the hairs גילוח? giluach? If
גילוח giluach means a cutting action, it's certainly not that. So if
you look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, not the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the ריב"ן,
Rivan, he says גילוח עבדי, השחתתן עושה גילוח כלומר גילוח מיקרי דדרך
לגלח בן אדם. giluach avdi, hashchatasan oseh giluach klomar giluach mikri de-derech
legaleach ben adam. That's also normal, which is a bit bizarre to
say it's completely not normal to do it that way. Okay, but
anyway, that's interesting that he's willing to consider it גילוח, giluach, which
might seem to indicate that he has a different definition of גילוח
giluach than the rabbis. Okay, moving on. Well then that could be
a problem, meaning getting back to... right, because if you want to
say that his definition should inform how we think the rabbis are
defining. הכותב כתובת קעקע, ha-kosev kesoves ka-aka, a writing of incision, so
meaning tattooing, okay, gets lashes. כתב ולא קיקע, kasav velo kikeia, I
guess, קיקע ולא כתב, kikeia velo kasav, if you did the ink
and you did not do the incision, or you did the incision,
which is like those fake tattoos they do nowadays, or you did
the incision without inking it, אינו חייב עד שיכתוב ויקעקע. eino chayav
ad she-yichtov ve-yakakeia. רש"י Rashi says the way it works, I have
no idea, is that you put ink on the skin and then
you cut into it and then the ink gets absorbed into the
skin and stays underneath. Nowadays they do it with like lasers, right?
What, how do they do it? I don't know. Anyway. Okay. Now,
אינו חייב עד שיכתוב ויקעקע. eino chayav ad she-yichtov ve-yakakeia. בדיו, be-dyo,
not בידו, be-yado, בדיו ובכחול, be-dyo uve-kochal, with ink or כחול kochal
is another type of a pigment, ובכל דבר שהוא רושם, uve-chol davar
she-hu roshem, anything that causes a pigmentation. רבי שמעון בן יהודה משום
רבי שמעון אומר אינו חייב עד שיכתוב שם את השם. Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehuda mishum Rabbi Shimon omer eino chayav ad she-yichtov sham es
ha-shem. You would have to write the name, sounds like God's name,
in your skin. שנאמר כתובת קעקע לא תתנו בכם אני ה'. shene'emar
kesoves ka-aka lo sitenu bachem Ani Hashem. אני ה'. Ani Hashem. It
sounds like you have to put אני ה' Ani Hashem into your
skin. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara is going to push back on
that. The גמרא Gemara is going to say, אמר ליה רב אחא
בריה דרבא לרב אשי עד שיכתוב אני ה' ממש? amar lei Rav
Achah berei de-Rava le-Rav Ashi ad she-yichtov Ani Hashem mamash? Literally? Until
he writes the words אני ה', Ani Hashem, like that's the עבירה?
aveirah? אמר ליה, amar lei, no, no, no, that's not the name
he meant. כדתני בר קפרא אינו חייב עד שיכתוב שם עבודה זרה,
ki-detani Bar Kappara eino chayav ad she-yichtov shem avodah zarah, which is
not what השם Hashem sounds like in the משנה. mishna. No, no,
no, it's the opposite. It has to be a writing of a
כתובת קעקע kesoves ka-aka that is a violation of אני ה', Ani
Hashem, not the words of אני ה'. Ani Hashem. Well, he's reading
it that way, again, this all works very nicely according to רמב"ם
that thinks the original context is עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay. שנאמר
כתובת קעקע לא תתנו בכם אני ה'. shene'emar kesoves ka-aka lo sitenu
bachem Ani Hashem. אני ה' ולא אחר, Ani Hashem velo acher, don't
have some other name of some other god branded on you, like
he means like you belong to this other god. I mean, the
גמרא Gemara in some places sort of compares like the idea of
תפילין tefillin like as a type of a branding, I think maybe
even a ברית מילה, bris milah, you know, the idea like I
belong to God, right? So here it's like be the branding of
a different god. Okay, now, אמר רב מלכייא אמר רב אדא בר
אהבה אסור לו לאדם שיתן אפר מקלה, amar Rav Malkiya amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava assur lo le-adam she-yiten efer mikleh, you can't put
ashes על גבי מכתו al gabi makato rub them into your wound
because then they will remain beneath your skin when the wound heals
and it'll look like a type of a tattoo. Now, you didn't
do any cutting, you just put it in an open wound, okay,
but nevertheless it'll look like you did. Wait, that's sort of a
problem. I mean, let's say that was an accepted medical remedy, you
couldn't do it? Correct. I mean, if it's פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh
or whatever, it's a different story. Anyway, מפני שנראה ככתובת קעקע, mipnei
she-nireh ki-kesoves ka-aka, because it would look like a type of... people
would see a pigment, an ink stain underneath your skin. אמר רב
נחמן בריה דרב עיקא, amar Rav Nachman berei de-Rav Ika, now there's...
the גמרא Gemara did some... where it tries to identify... there's a
רב מלכייא Rav Malkiya and a רב מלכיו, Rav Malkiyo, and there's...
and they each said like three statements, and we have to identify
who said who. So he says the following: שפוד שפחות וגומות, shevud
shefachos ve-gumos, the teaching of a שפוד shevud which is like on
יום טוב Yom Tov if you used a spit for making meat
or whatever you have to put it aside, it becomes disgusting after
it's used. Anyway, שפחות shefachos is a woman who brings in many
maidservants into a marriage, whether she still has certain wifely duties in
terms of household maintenance. And גומות gumos is when a child has
pubic hairs, the pubic hairs have to be coming from like what's
called like little indents in the skin. And if there are indents
without the hairs coming from it, is that still considered a סימן
siman that they're an adult? So those teachings about those things is
רב מלכייא Rav Malkiya said them. בלורית, bilurit, certain way hair is
cut like an עבודה זרה avodah zarah type of a cut of
the hair, אפר מקלה, efer mikleh, the ashes, which is our teaching
about ashes into an open wound, and גבינה, gvina, and questions about
why cheese of non-Jews is forbidden, so then... those teachings was רב
מלכיה, Rav Malkia, רב מלכיה Rav Malkia said it. רב פפא Rav
Papa אמר מתניתין matnisin ומתניתא u-matnisa רב מלכיה, Rav Malkia, no, no,
no, the משניות mishnos and the ברייתות braisos because some of these
were explanations of משניות mishnos and ברייתות. braisos. So the משניות mishnos
and the ברייתות braisos was רב מלכיה, Rav Malkia, שמעתתא shmaitata the
Amoraic teachings that were independent teachings were רב מלכיו. Rav Malkio. Now,
how does that change the lineup? וסימנך, vesimanach, now first of all
the way you know is מתניתא מלכתא. masnisa malkasa. מתניתא, masnisa, which
is like a feminine because it ends with an a sound and
sounds feminine, is מלכיה Malkia is also like an a sound, right,
is the, so the משניות mishnos are the queens, are the, you
know, they're the, they're the important ones, okay, anyway, מלכתא. malkasa. Anyway,
so you know that רב מלכיה Rav Malkia is the one, מלכתא
malkasa is the one that says the stuff that explains the משניות
mishnos and the ברייתות. braisos. מאי בינייהו? mai beinaiu? Now you have
to know what those are. So what would, how would that change
the list? איכא בינייהו שפחות. ika beinaiu shfachos. Because שבוד shvud and
גומות gumot are not explaining משניות mishnos and ברייתות, braisos, and שפחות
shfachos is explaining a משנה. mishna, So the שפחות shfachos would take
out of the list of רב מלכיו Rav Malkio and put it
into the list of רב מלכיה. Rav Malkia. Now the other things
in the רב מלכיה Rav Malkia list, so where's the other things
in the רב מלכיה Rav Malkia list? בלורית blorith is explaining a
משנה, mishna, גבינה gvinah is explaining a משנה, mishna אפר מקלה efer
mikleh however is not. So what it probably means is you exchange
the שפחות shfachos teaching which is a teaching on a משנה mishna
with the אפר מקלה efer mikleh teaching. You reverse those. Okay, whatever.
Moving on. Yes, there's a comment at the edge that the ashes
is discussing only a particular type, that the blackened ashes from made
from wood in a fuel stove, but there are other ashes you
could use for medical purposes that wouldn't leave as permanent a... okay,
so that's interesting. He's focusing on the word אפר מקלה efer mikleh
because what does the word מקלה mikleh as a modifier. So the
רשב"ם Rashbam also says, the רשב"ם, Rashbam, I keep on saying the
רשב"ם, Rashbam, the ריב"ן Rivon here also says by אפר מקלה efer
mikleh he says, if you look at it, he says... דווקא קאמר
לפי שקשה היא ומקטיעא משום המכה והרושם נראה שם אחר זמן. davka
kamar, lefi shekasha hi umkataiah mishum hamakah veharoshem nirah sham achar zman.
It's about like four lines down after the גמרא. Gemara. אבל עפר
בעלמא לא. aval afar be'alma lo. So the question is what does
the word מקלה mikleh come to modify? So if you look at
it, first he says only אפר מקלה efer mikleh because it really
leaves a lasting... you know impression, not impression, a lasting whatever mark,
but not עפר בעלמא. afar be'alma. עפר afar with an ע ayin
is dirt. So sometimes some say that the word מקלה mikleh only
comes to distinguish אפר efer from עפר, afar, because sometimes they're used
as synonyms, but really אפר efer is ashes and עפר afar is
dirt. So read that way, it's only saying ash, we mean ashes
here, we don't mean dirt. But whoever you're reading in your footnote
presumably understands that even within ashes we're only limiting it, who does
he quote here? ריטב"א. Ritva. Well, first it says any type any
other type of ash or dust is permitted, that's ריטב"א, Ritva, and
then it says see רמ"א Rama and תוספות. Tosfos. Yeah, so I
don't know if the ריטב"א Ritva is actually saying other ashes, the
ריטב"א Ritva is distinguishing ashes from dirt. But anyway, whatever it would
be, the point is is that stuff that leaves a lasting mark.
Yes, so then there's a question of how lasting is lasting. So
if I, if I write a note to myself with a ballpoint
pen, that eventually comes off, but it takes a while. Right, but
it also has to be under the skin, not over the skin.
Alright, so anyway it says like this, רב אימי בר אבא קפיד
אפילו אריבדא דכוסילתא. Rav Imi bar Abba kapad afilu arivda dekuslisa. He
did not even want somebody to use like a type of a
cutting thing that was used in the skin to... how do they
describe it, some type of a cutting thing that was used in
the skin to... a lancet. Oh, for like piercing a boil or
something like that. Because he was afraid that that might make incidentally
a mark. Okay. רב אשי אמר כל מקום שיש שם מכה מכתה
מוכיח עליו. Rav Ashi amar kol makom sheyesh sham makah makaso mochiach
alav. So this pushes back seemingly on both points, which is if
there's some type of a wound and you're doing this and you're
doing some stuff that's maybe leaving a mark, but you're doing it
to cut into a wound or whatever, then you know it's clear
that it's because of the wound and you're not transgressing. Now it's
very interesting here what some of the scope of this is. On
the first case where you're rubbing the ashes into the wound, you're
not actually making an incision. If you're cutting into the wound, okay,
and you are making an incision, but you're doing it for medical
purposes, okay, but it is making a mark, how much do you
say so is it that I, so maybe I did transgress? What
do you care מכתה מוכיח עליו? makaso mochiach alav? I cut in,
I left a lasting mark, does it have to be with the
intention to make a mark and if it's incidental it's not a
problem? Like why exactly, right, in the first case you weren't doing
the cutting, you were just rubbing into the wound. But if you're
doing a cutting but for medical purposes and incidentally it makes a
mark, have you transgressed but it's only like אינו מתכוון eino miskaven
or if you didn't do it for the sake of making a
mark it's not an issue? Like that's not clear. On this issue
comes up very much, there's actually a very much contemporary question that
comes up about women that had breast... Mastectomy and then they have
like reconstructive surgery and there's actually a tattooing that goes to recreate
the area, what's it called, the areola around the nipple to make
it look natural, so is that a biblical transgression of כתובת קעקע?
Kesovet Ka'aka? So, you know, so according to the רמב״ם Rambam it
wouldn't be right because the whole thing is עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah?
Okay, so the רמב״ם's Rambam's explanation of טעמי המצוות taamei hamitzvos is
that you don't get to sort of say like the רמב״ם Rambam
also thinks that כשרות kashrus is about health, you don't get to
say you're allowed to eat pork nowadays because it's healthy. I mean
if you can find in the גמרא Gemara that it's defined by
some of those contexts and parameters, it's one thing, but you don't
get to just sort of apply טעמי המצוות. taamei hamitzvos. So if
in the גמרא, Gemara. so some want to say, and this I
find a very hard read based on the גמרא Gemara and have
like almost no sources in the Talmudic, but there's definitely פוסקים Poskim
that rely on this. There's one אחרון Acharon that argues it's only
דאורייתא de-Oraisa if it's writing. If it's marks without writing, because the
word כתובת, Kesovet, כתיבה, kseivah, it'd have to be like letters or
some type of, I mean I don't know what would he say
a picture? But certainly something that is like not a word or
not a picture and just a mark, he would say is not.
Now there's no hint of that in the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא
Gemara spoke about the problem of rubbing ashes in and leaving a
mark and didn't indicate that that made any difference. Okay, but there's
definitely a lot of פוסקים that rely on that and say it's
only דרבנן, derabbanan, so it's for enough of a need etc. etc.
So you say it's דרבנן derabbanan if it's not writing? Actual letters.
I don't know, would that have to be like make a word
or just do ABC? No, I think I don't know, you'd have
to read him, presumably he would pictures would also be a problem,
but something that is סתם stam a mark, okay, which is you
understand the סברא svara to him, but the question is is it
based on anything? I think that there's more things to say about
like when the גמרא Gemara says one says because of the מכה
maka that maybe if it's not done for the purpose of like
disfiguring the body, you know, or changing the body, but here it's
actually restoring the body, okay, because there's even a גמרא Gemara that
talks about like branding slaves that seems like that might not be
a problem, which is bizarre, that would you think that would be
a classic problem of like a type of branding of slaves. So
anyway it's a very interesting question of exactly what the parameters are.
Okay, let's try to use the next two minutes at least turn
the page. Right, right, I think it could be writing like in
ancient right, right, I think it could be writing like in ancient
language and it could be a language, right, exactly. Okay, נזיר שהיה
שותה יין כל היום, Nazir shehayah shosah yayin kol hayom, so we
mentioned this משנה mishna, earlier, if a נזיר Nazir was drinking wine
the entire day, אינו חייב אלא אחת, eino chayiv ela achas, it's
only one transgression because it was one warning and the whole thing
is considered an ongoing process. אמרו לו אל תשתה אל תשתה, amru
lo al tish-teh al tish-teh, if he got warnings between the various
acts, והוא שותה, vehu shoseh, חייב על כל אחת ואחת, chayiv al
kol achas ve-achas, and each one is a distinct act with a
distinct warning and you get lashes for each one. היה מטמא למתים
כל היום, hayah mitameh le-meisim kol hayom, אינו חייב אלא אחת, eino
chayiv ela achas, if he spent the whole day visiting cemeteries, okay,
different cemeteries even though like it's a three hour drive from one
to the next, it's like ממה נפשך, mi-mah nafshach, either it's a
separate act and it didn't have a warning, only the first act
had a warning, or if you consider it one continuous act, then
if it's one continuous act, it's also only one set of lashes.
אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino chayiv ela achas. אמרו לו אל תטמא
אל תטמא amru lo al titama al titama והוא מטמא, vehu mitameh,
but if they warn him before each act, then each one is
distinct, the warning makes it distinct, and then each one has a
warning with it, in that case חייב על כל אחת ואחת, chayiv
al kol achas ve-achas, he gets on each separate one. But if
he's there the whole time and not in a different, no we're
not talking, that's a separate question if you're שוהה בבית הקברות, shoheh
be-veis hakvaros, we're not dealing with that. היה מגלח כל היום, hayah
megaleach kol hayom, אינו חייב אלא אחת, eino chayiv ela achas, he
was shaving the whole day, going back to our shaving case, okay,
he's shaving he's very slowly, very slowly, so only one. אמרו לו
אל תגלח אל תגלח amru lo al tigaleach al tigaleach והוא מגלח
vehu megaleach חייב על כל אחת ואחת. chayiv al kol achas ve-achas.
Okay, and so again that raised the question why we mentioned the
five corners, what's the significance of the five, anyway whatever, same point
here. היה לבוש בכלאים כל היום, hayah lavush be-kilayim kol hayom, now
here gets to Michael's question, let's say it's not a separate act,
let's say it's just staying in a state, okay, he was wearing
שעטנז sha'atnez all day, אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino chayiv ela achas.
אמרו לו אל תלבש אל תלבש amru lo al tilbash al tilbash
והוא פושט ולובש, vehu poshet velovesh, not staying, if he takes off
the clothes and puts them back on, now just taking them off
and putting them back on he wouldn't get separate lashes, we would
still consider it, so there was only one warning, so we'd either
consider it separate acts without the other ones didn't have warnings or
one process, either way if without separate warnings you're only going to
get one set of lashes, but if he was taking off and
putting on and each separate act had a warning with it, okay,
I'm sorry, excuse me, אל תלבש והוא פושט ולובש, al tilbash vehu
poshet velovesh, so there's separate warning and a separate act of taking
off and putting on, חייב על כל אחת ואחת, chayiv al kol
achas ve-achas, he gets for every one. יש חורש, yesh choresh, will
finish the משנה, mishna, so the גמרא is mostly going to ignore
the first half of the משנה, mishna. which is fascinating in terms
of its defining separate acts, but we've discussed it before that the
warnings separate the acts, we're going to really focus on this part
of the משנה. Mishna. יש חורש תלם אחד וחייב עליו משום שמונה
לאוין. yesh choresh telem echad vechayiv alav mishum shemoneh lavin. Somebody can
make one furrow and do eight עבירות aveiros with one furrow. החורש
בשור וחמור, hachoresh beshor vachamor, you have an ox and a donkey,
that's one עבירה, aveira, והם מוקדשים, vehem mukdashim, they're הקדש, hekdesh, so
we're going to see the בכור bechor is the... The ox is
a בכור bechor and the חמור, chamor, let's say for now, argument's
sake it's old debate of רש"י תוספות, Rashi Tosfos, is sanctified בדק
הבית. bedek habayis. So for the ox you're transgressing לא תעבד בבכר
שורך, lo saavod bivchor shorecha, that you're working a בכור, bechor, and
by the donkey that's הקדש בדק הבית, hekdesh bedek habayis, you're just
transgressing let's say מעילה, me'ila, okay? So that's three. וכלאיים, v'kilayim, okay,
בכרם. b'kerem. Now what you happen to be doing in your plowing
is planting, you know, grape seeds and other seeds together, כלאיים. kilayim.
Yeah, but that's the planting, that's not the plowing. So the גמרא
says that the plow as you're plowing the dirt covers over the
seeds, so it's a type of a planting. But yes, we have
because we have to make it one act. ובשביעית, u'vishvi'is, it's שמיטה,
shmitta, so you're not allowed to plow on שמיטה, shmitta, that's five.
ויום טוב, v'Yom Tov, you're not allowed to plow on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, that's six. וכהן ונזיר בבית הטומאה. v'Kohen v'Nazir b'veis hatuma.
Oh and by the way you happen to be in a cemetery
and you're a כהן Kohen and a נזיר. Nazir. Now that's a
cheat because that's not has nothing to do with plowing, that has
to do with just where you are. So that's what חנניה Chananya
says in the משנה. חנניה בן חכינאי אומר אף הלובש כלאיים. Chananya
ben Chakinai omer af halovesh kilayim. Oh, well let's say you're wearing
שעטנז shatnes while you're doing it and eating a cheeseburger. אמרו לו,
amru lo, they said to him, אינו מן השם. eino min hashem.
Oh no, that's not the same act. אמר להם, amar lahem, אף
נזיר לא מן השם. af nazir lo min hashem. So what? So
the נזיר Nazir and the כהן being in a cemetery isn't the
same act, which is a pretty darn good argument. That's not about
plowing, that's just about where you happen to be. So I don't
understand why the חכמים Chachamim made a distinction anyway. It's all, there's
no halachic mastery here, we're just having fun seeing how many things
you can get in. תוספות, Tosfos, by the way, thinks that the
שור shor and the חמור, chamor, that the, that it's only one
thing when they're הקדש, hekdesh, that it's בכור, bechor, the חמור chamor
is not a בכור. bechor. And he says, he, so he makes
up the one because he doesn't have the חמור chamor being הקדש
בדק הבית, hekdesh bedek habayis, he makes it up by saying you're
planting both כלאי כרם kilay kerem and כלאי זרעים. kilay zraim. There
are three things, there are two different types of seeds from different
types of let's say, you know, wheat and barley or whatever and
a grape seed. So it's both a transgression of כלאי כרם kilay
kerem and a transgression of כלאי זרעים. kilay zraim. That's how he
gets it because if you count it really it's not so clear
why there's eight rather than seven. All right, we'll pick up with
this tomorrow.